we have learned very recently a lot of
information about what explains why some
people can do things like eat more
calories eat more food but yet not gain
as much weight as you that is a real
phenomenon even when all other variables
are controlled for that can happen but
that's not explained by having a faster
or slower metabolism so let's imagine a
scenario in which you consume and burn
exactly 2,000 calories per day so you're
net equal and at that you keep the exact
same level of muscle and energy and
recovery and performance and body fat
and so on and so forth if I could do
that exact same thing at 4,000
calories now I've got much more options
what I mean by that is if I can keep you
at the exact same for all those
variables at Double the caloric load
I've got a greater ability to increase
my food intake which means my
micronutrients go up if I eat double the
food I get double the vitamins and
minerals and nutrients and fiber intake
and if I'm staying at the exact same
body composition body mass that is a
huge Advantage additionally it now
becomes far easier to lose weight if you
ever want to do that one of the things
that makes it really hard for weight
loss if your metabolism is quote unquote
slow again think that total input versus
output is low say 2,000 and you want to
drop it by say 500 calories you've
reduced a significant portion of of your
caloric intake you're going to feel that
and you've dropped a quarter of your
calories however if you're at 4,000
calories Turn and Burn and we drop you
by
500 now we've only lowered your intake
by a small percentage and so you don't
feel that much of a difference you won't
really feel 3500 calories versus 4,000
calories but you'll feel 15 versus 2,000
even though in both cases is exactly 500
calories and so for a lot of people
there is still a huge interest in
understanding and making your overall
metabolism function how you want for
both the short and long term regardless
of whether or not body composition or
body fat is your primary secondary or
even of slight interest to you right now
now I can continue talking about that
Delta and why you want to avoid energy
toxicity but you do at the same time
want to have a high caloric intake but
we'll save those thoughts for another
conversation we want to get really into
today's topic and so what is speeding up
your metabolis is M even mean and I've
been using a bunch of different terms
thus far on purpose I've tried to throw
out misconceptions I've used the wrong
phrase intentionally because that's how
it's used colloquially that's probably
how you've heard it and that's how
you've thought about it so I've done
that uh with direct intent there we're
going to talk about what those things
mean we're going to talk about what it
actually means to have a fast or slow
metabolism and so let's get into those
very basic parts right now
scientifically metabolism is the net of
all cellular processes in your entire
body so when you're metabolizing
hormones or proteins or energy
substrates like carbohydrates and fat
all of that is combined together to make
up your metabolism so that is a giant
net it is not specifically and only
referring to the calories in versus
calories out what you're burning for
exercise or your body fat composition it
is all things going on that is an
incredibly difficult number to come up
with it is not a rate it is a total
amount what what I mean by that is it's
not a speed this is why I can tell you
people in our field and mind you I've
got a PhD in human
bioenergetics so people in this field
will tell you there is no speed
component here it is a total rate
component and so the analogy I'll give
you here is a car okay now if I had you
driving in your car at 50 mil an hour
and we increased you to 70 M hour your
speed went up okay when people think
about boosting their metabolism that's
what they think happens I'm driving
faster and when we say you don't speed
up your metabolism when I tell you yours
is the same speed as mine what I mean is
we're all driving at 50 miles hour but
at the same time I also did tell you we
can raise it and that there are some
people who can handle more energy and
not gain as much and so forth that's not
a speed issue what that is is the total
amount of drive time right it is not
speeding up your metabolism it is going
through metabolism more frequently
that's effectively what's happening so
it's driving more often if you drive
more often let's say again the analogy
of speed here we're both driving at 50
miles per hour you don't speed up or
slow down but I drive for one mile and
you drive for 15 who burned more gas you
did that's exactly what we're talking
about so somebody with a fast metabolism
is someone who simply driving for 15
miles and someone with a slow metabolism
is somebody who's driving for 5 miles or
2 mil miles or whatever the case may be
that is incredibly important because we
as we start getting into claims in the
field and misconceptions and improper
marketing they're going to use those
things as tricks and ways to twist you
so easy examples there's plenty of
supplements that you can take that will
quote unquote speed up your metabolism
they will turn it on they will get you
going but they do not result in any
additional fat loss for mechanisms in
which we will cover later and so
understanding the very basic principle
there lets you realize okay great they
can make a certain claim there but in
reality it is what I'm trying to hear is
that product will help me lose fat more
and that will not be the case that is
often what we see and have historically
heard in the magazines in the media with
the supplement companies and so forth
regarding speeding up your metabolism so
now that you understand that you're not
going to fall a prey to that trick again
so here's what we really mean when
people say I want a faster metabolism or
my metabolism is slow and so they say my
metabolism is too slow or I want it to
go faster what do they really saying
they're generally talking about body
composition I hate to phrase it this way
I didn't want to do it because there's
so much more to metabolism than just
body comp but again this is a very easy
entry point for us so we'll stay here
just so most people can understand so
when they're saying that my metabolism
is slow what they're usually saying is a
comment about their body composition
they have more fat than they would like
it's hard for them to lose fat it's hard
for them to gain muscle or the opposite
someone who complains of a fast
metabolism is somebody who's having a
hard time gaining muscle I eat and I eat
and I eat I just can't gain I eat and I
eat I just can't gain so there's there's
complaints on both sides of the equation
example here just to give you some math
let's say both you and your friend eat
1,500 calories a day and let's say we
live in a magical universe and stress
and sleep and all that is all equated
for the only difference between you
you both add 1500 calories per day for
eight weeks one of you loses 3 PB the
other loses 12 PB that is a real thing
that can and does happen it's easy then
for you to think okay tabolism Fast
Metabolism slope so what's really
happening there is a change in what we
call
TDE or total daily energy expenditure
when you hear the phrase fast and slow
metabolism where the phrase is I want
you to think total daily energy
expenditure now that has four unique
components and I'll cover in one second
but the reality it is what could be
explaining that person who lost more
weight than you did or didn't gain as
much whether you're in a caloric Surplus
or choric deficit it doesn't matter
something in that total daily energy
expenditure was different for them there
is no in that component that is
metabolic speed but that's the
translation all right so boost
metabolism is really an increase or
decrease in total daily energy
expenditure if you want to look at total
body mass body composition we can look
at this as simply as our energy
expenditure versus our energy intake a
lot of times you'll see this abbreviated
is EI energy intake so I can increase or
decrease my weight by changing either
side of my equation for example if I
increased my total daily energy
expenditure of which I have four ways to
do that four components but if I
increase that and I didn't increase my
intake my body mass will go down or I
could keep my energy expenditure the
same and I could lower my energy intake
okay or combinations of both but that's
honestly what we're what we're talking
about when we're discussing metabolic
speed I'm actually fine with people
saying I've sped up my metabolism as
long as we're using it appropriately in
this context I don't like to use it but
I absolutely get it why most folks do
and so total daily energy expenditure as
I said has four components what are
those four components the first one is
what we call eat eat some people call
this e what we're effectively talking
about is exercise so eat stands for the
exercise activity thermogenesis it's the
calories you burn during exercise e is
energy expenditure it doesn't matter how
you think about this but it's how many
calories did you burn in your workout
for most people that's going to
represent somewhere between Z to
30% of their total daily energy
expenditure so just to make sure you're
following me of all the calories you
burn throughout the day everything
combined if you don't work out well then
none of their caloric expenditure is
going to be explained by exercise most
people though probably going to have 10
to 20% of the calories they burn
throughout the day coming from exercise
folks that really training a lot maybe
closer to 20 25 or even up to 30% it's
hard to get past 30% you would have to
train a ton but you can generally think
10 20% of your energy throughout the day
coming from
calories we will talk about this later
but this is one of the reasons why and
and I it will explain very clearly why
this is the wrong thing to think but
this is the F some people use to say
things like oh exercise doesn't even
help with fat loss and they're not not
entirely wrong here because it's not
explaining the largest part of your
caloric expenditure 10% even for someone
who works out pretty often or pretty
hard 90% of the calories you're burning
are from things not exercised so they're
not completely unfounded though again I
think it's really terrible advice we'll
talk about that and the research on it
in detail later but again component
number one of total daily energy
expenditure is exercise component number
two is similar to eat which is called
neat so it's eat with an n in front of
it it is non exercise activity
thermogenesis this is all the other
physical activity you're doing
throughout the day that is not
structured and specific
exercise this is everything from
fidgeting to walking pacing taking the
stairs going uh parking further in the
parking lot so you walk more it is all
of those other things that are still
going to expend calories but they're not
exercise one of the interesting things
about this is this has often times as
much if not a bigger component of your
total energy expenditure than structured
exercise does people have completely
forgotten about this but the reality of
it is it's going to be somewhere between
5 to 30% of your
TDE the next two components are what's
called your TEF and I apologize for all
the acronyms here I'm trying to really
make sure we walk you through it I I
think you're holding on this far it is
the thermal effect of food this is quite
simply
the energies or the heat you create in
response to breaking down food in your
stomach so the reality is when you eat
food items they sit in your stomach you
have to burn some calories to digest
them if you want to think about it that
way and that then creates some choric
expenditure it's usually about 8 to 15%
of your TDE and so if you add eat neat
and TEF up what you have remaining of
that 100% is your resting metabolic rate
and that ranges from about 40% % of TDE
all the way up to 80% especially in
folks that are sedentary or lowly active
so as we get into this how I'm going to
cover the intervention and the research
is which area of total daily energy
expenditure is each given protocol or
intervention influencing so what can we
do to increase our eat what can we do to
increase neat TEF as well as resting
metabolic rate the reality as I said at
the beginning I think it's best that you
tried to implement a well-rounded plan
that influences all four of these
components or at least multiple of them
but if you can't exercise say you're
injured or bedridden or you're in
another scenario where you can't
exercise or whatever the case may be you
have other options and that's why I want
to present all this stuff is so you know
no matter what situation you're in based
on preference or realistic or
feasibility or Effectiveness you can
alter your metabolism in in multiple
Fashions to make sure that your body
composition and overall energy intake is
where you want it to be whether that's
loss gain or maintenance for that matter
if you enjoyed this clip you can watch
the full episode by clicking here